Edwin Augustus Porcher Collection
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
- Drawings, Series I
  - Drawings in North Africa (associated with the Nathan Davis expedition)
    - 79. General view of the site of Utica. June 10th, 1858. Published., 1858 June 10; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 26 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 2)
      This watercolor was engraved and published as "A View of the Site of Utica" in Nathan Davis' Carthage and Her Remains (page 414). The engraving omits the seated figures and inverts the two main figures and the horse, adding a running figure with a musket. Davis writes: "At the exact time specified by Lord Lyons, HM steamer "Harpy" arrived. She was commanded by Lieut. Porcher, who was instructed by the admiral not only to convey me to the sites of the various ancient cities above named, but to render me every assistance in his power – instructions which this officer was ready to carry out, and did carry out to the best of his abilities." Porcher and his crew (praised by Davis as "sturdy marines") assisted with the removal and transportation of a number of mosaics and sculpture from the excavation site at Utica, which according to Davis was once on the water but now "seven or eight miles' distance from the sea". Utica aided Rome in the destruction of Carthage. Davis describes the area as already "ransacked of building materials," and yet "marble and granite shaft, capitals, and cornices of every order, size and dimension, which lie about here in all directions, are certainly a great attraction for antiquarian research" (409).
      B1977.14.22171
      Watercolors; Utica (Extinct city)
    - 80. Ruins of the arsenal at Utica. May 24th, 1858., 1858 May 24; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 25.25 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 2)
      B1977.14.22168
      Excavations (Archaeology); Watercolors; Utica (Extinct city)
    - 81. A hot mineral spring under the nearest date tree, amongst the ruins of Utica. June 10th, 1858., 1858 June 10; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 26 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 2)
      B1977.14.22172
      Utica (Extinct city); Hot springs; Watercolors
    - A mosaic pavement (measuring 11.3 feet by 5) taken up at Utica on June 12th, 1858, and sent home to the British museum. Published., 1858 June 12; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 25.5 x 18 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 2)
      A wash drawing diagram of the 'hunters mosaic' found in Utica. This may have been used to prepare the engraving "Plan of a Chamber Discovered at Utica" for Nathan Davis' Carthage and Her Remains (page 417). "On close inspection of this ruin, I decided on sinking a shaft at a spot which I believed was beyond the wall. A few hours of careful digging brought to light another mosaic, placed upon a raised semicircular alcove, appertaining to the same chamber. It represents a water-scene, and contains eleven different sorts of animals, among which I may mention the board, the leopard, the ostrich, the stag, etc." A net with floats, hauled by two men in 'curiously shaped canoes', led Davis to call this the 'Hunters Mosaic.' Positing that the scene represents an 'inundation,' the mosaic lends further proof to Davis's theory that Utica was originally a maritime city (419).
      Mounted on the same card with "83. Ruins of a Theatre at Utica. May 21st, 1858. Published."
      B.1977.14.22166
      Watercolors; Antiquities; Mosaics, Ancient; Utica (Extinct city)
    - 83. Ruins of a theatre at Utica. May 21st, 1858. Published., 1858 May 21; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 25.5 x 18 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 2)
      Mounted with Porcher's diagram of the "hunters mosaic", this watercolor was the basis for an engraving of the same name in Nathan Davis' Carthage and Her Remains (page 405). Davis describes the site: "In the direction of the cape we have the remains of a theatre, which must have been gorgeously decorated, judging from the numerous fragments of rich marbles which are here found" (408). The archaeologist forms the theory that the theater was practical for the representation of naval battles, as water could be dispensed from the nearby aqueduct into the amphitheater, then emptied into the harbor below. He concludes: "A double object was thus attained: the people were gratified by an attractive exhibition, and the public reservoirs were regularly cleansed" (407).
      Mounted on the same card with "A Mosaic pavement (measuring 11.3 feet by 5) taken up at Utica on June 12th, 1858, and sent home to the British museum. Published."
      B1977.14.22167
      Watercolors; Utica (Extinct city); Excavations (Archaeology)
    - 84. The fortified town of Bizerta, in the Regency of Tunis taken from H.M. Schooner Kertch. June 16th 1860., 1860 June 16; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 25 x 35.5 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 2)
      The northernmost city in Africa, Bizerta is 40 miles north of Tunis, and 18 miles north of Utica. The date of this watercolor indicates that it was sketched after the completion of Nathan Davis's expedition, during one of Porcher's three return trips to Tunis in 1860.
      B1977.14.22195
      Watercolors; Bizerte (Tunisia); Fortification; Kertch (Ship)
    - 85. The island of Tabarkah in the Regency of Tunis. June 19th 1860., 1860 June 19; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 25.25 x 35.5 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 2)
      B1977.14.22196
      Watercolors; Tabarqah (Tunisia)
    - 86. The village of Tabarkah. [Tunis] June 26th 1860., 1860 June 26; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 23.5 x 35.5 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 2)
      Tabarka is a coastal town situated in the northwest of Tunisia.
      B1977.14.22197
- Diary and logbooks, Series II
  - Diary, 1851 September – 1853 January; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 volume (68 pages): 8 pen and ink drawings; 18 x 12 cm (Box Vol. 1)
    Holograph diary, labelled: "E.A. Porcher. Notes on Ports Visited in H.M.S. CLEOPATRA, September 1851 – circa 1853". Includes the following small pen and ink drawings: "purchase for hauling vessels up at Jardine's slip" (page 7), chart (18), map of Labuan (20), diagram (25), 2 sketches (26), sketch of a lighthouse (45) and a map of Amoy (55).
    Porcher provides general descriptions of the ports visited by the Cleopatra, including hydrographical information, natural resources, natural history, and inhabitants. The diary is roughly divided into sections describing the following topics: the island and harbor of Hong Kong; monsoons, currents, and other weather patterns affecting navigation of the China Sea; Labuan; A Conflict with Pirates in Borneo, 1852; the Straits of Singapore; Shanghai; Amoy; Macau; Hong Kong's population; Burma.
    Porcher begins with Hong Kong, describing its general topographical character, soil, climate, measurements, demographics, and geology. The main feature of the island is "the secure and convenient harbor," which he notes has "induced the English plenipotentiary to select this island, and owing to the few inhabitants becomes a much safer retreat for the English in case of another misunderstanding with the Chinese" (1-2). Hong Kong is preferable to nearby Chusan, in Porcher's view, which had a number of islands where pirates could easily hide or escape. Upriver at Whampoa, an island where foreign traders would unload their cargo onto smaller vessels to take up the narrow Straits to Canton, Porcher lists some foreign vessels at the dry dock such as the "Villa de Bilboa" (a Spanish frigate), a patent slip in Jardine's establishment, and the "Royalist," the steamer "Canton" (6). As a result of the European populace who resided there for several months of each year, Whampoa became a cosmopolitan way-station between the Chinese city of Canton and the Portuguese colony of Macau.
    The diary provides valuable insight into how naval ships negotiated changing weather conditions in Hong Kong and in travel between South China sea ports. Pages 7-15 are devoted to explanations of meteorological information: the South-West monsoon, which occurs from April to October; the North-East Monsoon, which prevails from September or October in the north; typhoons on the southern coast in June and July; Gales that blow steadily in September on the China coast; and variable currents which depend on local wind, shoreline, and monsoon conditions. Porcher's log might have been intended for use by future officers in determining the best seasonal routes and naval maneuvers in the region.
    He provides a general description of the Island of Labuan, off the coast of Borneo, which was originally proposed as a British base against piracy in 1840 and became a Crown Colony in 1848. His descriptions strike a note of interest in the natural products and cultivation – information useful for determining Labuan's suitability for settlement and resource extraction. Particularly interested in raw materials such as camphor wood - valuable for its gum, oil, and use as insect repellent – and rattan for rigging and furniture, Porcher stresses that "the most important product is certainly the coal," he writes, "both in a political as well as commercial view" (23). This point was of strategic importance to the British navy, as a steady supply of coal was essential for steamship operations, and "should the steam route through the Eastern Archipelago come into practice, this coal district would be of vast importance" (24). Porcher also speculates that the island could be conducive to the lucrative cultivation of cotton, sugar, rice, coffee (27). Another of its exports is leeches, evidently still used to treat disease.
    Pages 29-44 of Porcher's diary are devoted to incidents in early 1852, in which members of the Cleopatra's crew was dispatched on the steamers Semiramis and Pluto to seek out pirates who had murdered the crew of a small trading schooner, the HMS Dolphin. With the Political Agent for Borneo and Captain Brooke from Sarawak accompanying the expedition, the Cleopatra first stopped at Gaya Bay in late January to meet with the Chief Pangeran Madand, "about his rendering the Illanun [Iranun] pirates assistance, particularly in selling them a boat in which they went pirating in" (30). Some marines disembark, but then all at once "the men in the boats were suddenly fired upon from the jungle, that grew close down to the water on each side, and one man killed and two wounded." (33). The next day (February 18), the boats return to the chief's house and burn forty houses and property in revenge for the previous day's ambush. The men in boats were again shot upon from the jungle – one killed, two wounded. Porcher illustrates select episodes from this incident (see "25. Official visit of the boats of the Cleopatra to the Pangeran Madoud's house […]" and "27. Borneo. Skirmish with the Illanoon pirates at Tooncoo […]"). Devoting pages 37-44 to a lengthy description of the Iranun pirates, he explains the details of the pirate escape routes, hideouts, vessels, and fighting weapons (42).
    With its rapidly increasing trade as a result of treaty port status, the formerly isolated trading center of Shanghai "is likely erelong to become the principal emporia in China" (48), speculates Porcher. Its advantageous position at the junction of two rivers allow communication with Suchow-fu, the capital, as well as Yunnan and Su'chuen [Sichuan?]. Merchandise such as silk, cotton, bamboo, bronze and earthenware attract interest, but food products most of all – "dining rooms, tea houses, and bakers shops are met with in at every step" (49). A temperature table "from Dr. Lockhart's hospital report" is included for comparison with Hong Kong's climate.
    Porcher describes the southwest corner of the island of Amoy [Xiamen] as "the most important harbor in the province of Fuhkien [Fujian]," delighting in the "picturesque" scenery caused by the number of pagoda-topped islands dotting the bay (52). At the western side of the harbour is Kulang-su [Gulanyu], littered with batteries and once occupied by English troops after the city's capture in 1841. Porcher is quick to recommend Kulang-su for English settlement, "in case of another misunderstanding with the Chinese," for its strategic position between high ridges and as a source of fresh water (53). Moreover, the location's lack of significant waves makes it an ideal spot for repair docks (54).
    Porcher describes Macau, the Portuguese colony, as "a far more healthy and agreeable residence than Hong Kong, on account of its being open to all breezes" (56). The lack of harbor in the vicinity is one drawback, however, that forces ships to anchor four miles away from the main town. He describes the means by which ships might pass the Typa anchor in the low water, and in monsoons. This description is followed by a population chart of Hong Kong for 1851, broken down into the demographics: Europeans and Americans (647); Goa and Macao Portuguese (489); Indians, Malays and Natives of Manita (221); aliens or temporary residents (13) and Chinese (31,983). The Chinese are then broken down by locations and occupations. A "map of Canton, Macao, Hong Kong, and the adjacent islands" on page 62 is in Porcher's characteristic, meticulous hand.
    In his last pages, Porcher conveys the dangers of running aground along the Rangoon (Burma/Myanmar) coast in the Southwest Monsoon, due to its "many creeks and rivers with reef and shoal water" (64). And yet braving this is well worth the trouble for the traveler, as the town is situated on the shore of a great river, and the magnificent Dagon Pagoda is "supposed to be the finest in this part of the country" (65). During the "last war," East India Company surveys penetrated up the river, and the town has "every prospect of being a very flourishing place, after it has been our possession a few years, it will make a good building establishment" (65). The area known as the Martaban or Salween river was ceded to the British government and the village of Amherst built on a peninsula on the mouth of the river. Moulmein [Mawlamyine], about 25 miles from Amherst, was founded as the principle British settlement on the northern boundary. A description and table of rainfall at Moulmein during the Southwest monsoons from 1845-52 completes Porcher's description of Rangoon's physical geography and meteorology.
    China Sea; Labuan; Pen and ink drawings; Maps; Macau (China); Diaries; Pirates; Harbors -- China; Hong Kong (China); Weather; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; Cleopatra (Ship: 1843)
  - Navigational Logbook, 1849 May – 1853 September; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 volume; 19.5 x 13 cm (Box Vol. 2, no. 1)
    Logbook recording daily positions during the HMS Cleopatra's tour of duty. It commences with an account of the weight of various articles on board and the dimensions of the HMS Cleopatra, 26 Guns. The vessel departed Plymouth on May 13, 1849. It anchored at Rio de Janeiro, Singapore, and Labuan before arriving at Hong Kong October 15, 1849. The vessel sailed to Bombay, Malacca, Penang and Madras in 1850 and made repeat trips to Singapore and the South China Seas. The Cleopatra made its return voyage to England (via Cape of Good Hope), and docked in September 1853.
    Navigation; China Sea; Pen and ink drawings; Ships' logs; Cleopatra (Ship: 1843)
  - Navigational Logbook, 1857 February – 1861 October; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 12 pages; 19.5 x 13 (Box Vol. 2, no. 2)
    Navigational logbook recording daily positions during his tour of duty in Malta and the Middle East on the HMS Hibernia, H.M. Paddle wheel Harpy, HMS Schooner Kertch, and HMS Boxer. Porcher departed England for Malta on the Screw Steam Ship Colombo (February 20, 1857). Joining the Harpy in May 1858, he sailed with the Rev. Nathan Davis to Goletta, Tunisia, to assist with the archaeological expedition. On October 29, 1859, he departed for Livorno ("Leghorn") and Naples, returning November 22 the same year. He sailed twice to Tunis on the Schooner Kertch, once in February 1860, and in June, 1860. He departed for Benghazi in the HMS Boxer in November 1860. The dates of Porcher and Smith's expedition to Cyrene are omitted, likely because it was not under the auspices of Her Majesty's Service, but the logbook picks up again on their return to Malta via the HMS Melpomene (under command of Captain Ewart) in October 1861.
    Mediterranean Sea -- Navigation; Ships' logs; Boxer (Ship: 1855-1865); Harpy (Ship: 1845-1909); Kertch (Ship); Hibernia (Ship: 1804-1902)
- Miscellaneous, Series III
  - "Sketches taken during my Voyages & Travels. E.A. Porcher.", circa 1860?; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; Melville, Harden Sidney, active 1837-1882; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
    B1977.14.22202
    This drawing, a frontispiece study for an unpublished publication or collection, combines visual elements from select locations of Porcher's travel, repeating motifs from his own work. Depicted are scenes from Australia (Aboriginal Australians or Torres Strait Islanders, upper left corner), Burma (stupa, center), India (elephant and howdah, lower right corner), Hong Kong (Chinese junk, center), the Middle East (scene from Tunisia or Libya, lower left). The albatross, while possibly a reference to Coleridge's Rime of the Ancient Mariner, could also be a quotation of Porcher's watercolor "The Wandering Albatross of the Indian Ocean, July 1842," (National Library of Australia). An erased signature "H.S. Melville" at bottom right matches existing signatures by Harden S. Melville.
    Voyages and travel; Watercolors; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878
  - List of "Original Sketches", Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 sheet (1 page): pen and ink on medium thick beige paper.; 33 x 19 cm (Box Oversize 1)
    Inventory of drawings associated with the HMS Cleopatra tour of duty, numbered. Handwriting matches that in Porcher's diary.
  - Sketch, 1859 July; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: pen and ink, watercolor; sheet 12 x 9 cm (Box Vol. 2, no. 3)
    Watercolor sketch of a young woman in blue dress, from behind. Inscribed at bottom: "Taken from the club steps Valetta, July 1859." Inscribed at top: "B.G. as seen from the club steps, Valetta, en route to [illegible]."
    Valletta (Malta); Clothing and dress; Watercolors
  - Sketch, ca. 1860?; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: graphite on paper; sheet 11 x 6.5 cm (Box Vol. 2, no. 4)
    Graphite sketch, with inscription: "Table laid, for our visitors at Cyrene"
    Cyrene (Extinct city); Graphite drawings; Dinners and dining
  - Envelope, circa 1860; 1 envelope; 9 x 13 cm (Box Vol. 2, no. 5)
    Pale blue envelope, addressed to "Lieutenant Porcher, HMS Hibernia." On the front of the envelope is printed "On Her Majesty's Service." The envelope previously contained the two small drawings listed above (items 3 and 4).
    Envelopes (Stationery); Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878
  - Letter to Madelina Porcher, 1849 December 29; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed, written in pen and black ink; 25 x 20 cm (Box Vol. 2, no. 6)
    Headed: "HMS Cleopatra, Hong Kong."
    A letter from Porcher to his sister, Madelina, in London. He expresses concern about the cholera epidemic in Europe. He also describes a trip to Canton with some fellow officers, which he obtained leave to conduct. He relates an outsider's view of the city around the 'factories' area, where foreigners were permitted to stay. He also describes Whampoa, the location where foreign boats docked: "This is a very stupid place… As the town is built on piles on a mud flat, but all the merchant shipping remains here, as they cannot get nearer Canton on account of the river being shallow about this." Hong Kong leisure activities is a topic of interest for Porcher, who lists a dinner with the Governor and the Club as the "chief amusement." However, he is careful to note the danger which the island presents to Englishmen: "it is not safe at present to go far into the country as there have been many murders lately."
    Hong Kong (China); Huangpu Qu (Guangzhou Shi, China); Guangzhou (China); Correspondence; Cholera; Porcher, Madelina -- Correspondence; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878 -- Correspondence
  - Letter to Madelina Porcher, 1852 May 24; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed, written in pen and black ink; 18 x 11.5 cm (Box Vol. 2, no. 7)
    Headed: "HMS Cleopatra, Hong Kong"
    A letter from Porcher to his sister, Madelina, in England. He relates his disappointment that it will be next Spring before he can return home, complaining of the hot weather. Relating news about the Second Anglo-Burmese War, he regrets not being able to join the naval forces dispatched to the region. Reporting another trip to Canton, Porcher writes of a public execution: "53 losing their heads, in about 2 minutes." Sketches of the event were sent to the Illustrated London News: "I will not repeat it as you will probably see it, a short time after you receive this."
    Guangzhou (China); Anglo-Burmese War, 2nd, 1852; Correspondence; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878 -- Correspondence; Porcher, Madelina -- Correspondence
  - Letter to Madelina Porcher, 1853 April 19; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed, written in pen and black ink; 18 x 11 cm (Box Vol. 2, no. 8)
    Headed: "HMS Cleopatra, Moulmein"
    A letter from Porcher to his sister, Madelina. Addressed from Moulmein (Mawlamyine) in Burma (Myanmar), which became the capital of the British colonial holdings following the First Anglo-Burmese war. Porcher laments that he will not be able to return yet from his tour of duty, as he is posted to assist with annexation of territories following the Second Anglo-Burmese War: "A steamer left Rangoon for Calcutta for more Troops, as we have not sufficient garrisoned all the places properly."
    Correspondence; Anglo-Burmese War, 2nd, 1852; Moulmein (Burma); Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878 -- Correspondence; Porcher, Madelina -- Correspondence
  - Certificate, 1853; Massie, Thomas Leeke, 1802-1898; 1 sheet (1 page): written in pen and black ink; 20.5 x 16.5 cm (Box Vol. 2, no. 9)
    Certificate signed by Captain T.L. Massie testifying to Porcher's service on board the HMS Cleopatra, from April 24, 1849, to September 20, 1853, "during which time he complied with the General Printed Instructions, and has kept a log, and journal."
    Certificates; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; Cleopatra (Ship: 1843)
  - Certificate, 1858 December 7; 1 sheet (1 page): letterpress, completed in pen and black ink; 20 x 16 cm (Box Vol. 2, no. 10)
    A certificate signed by Commander Roberts [?] testifying to Edwin Augustus Porcher's service aboard the HMS Hibernia, from February 10, 1857, to December 7, 1858.
    Certificates; Hibernia (Ship: 1804-1902); Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878